Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers records, 1749-2008.
Congregational Library & Archives
Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers records, 1749-2008.
RG0767
Congregational Library & Archives
1.57 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes, 2 reels)
The Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers began between 1692-94 when ministers in Massachusetts Bay met to consider contemporary issues facing their parishes. By the middle of the 20th-century, the convention became a center of religious dialogue for Massachusetts Congregational minister. The records contain meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, financial statements, photographs, and publications.
Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909
Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers
Wintersteen, Prescott Browning
Worthley, Harold Field
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Harold Worthley in 1974. Additional material were added to the collection in 2012 through a donation by Joseph Bassett. Transcriptions added to the collection in 2018 by a donation from the Worthley estate. Reporting Committee survery added to the collection in November 2018 by a donation from LaVonne E. Pippin; Accession 2018-38.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The following is an extract from The History of the Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers drafted by Joseph Bassett, the scribe of the Convention, in 2008:
"The Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers as we know it began between 1692-94 when ministers in Massachusetts Bay met to consider issues afoot in the land... By 1721 the Convention met to hear a Convention sermon in May followed by a dinner with members of the Great and General Court popularly known as The Feast of Moses an Aaron. In 1949 Professor George Williams ardently pled that the MCCM not fold its tent since it was the only Massachusetts clergy configuration not to split in the Unitarian controversy.
"Since 1973 a pattern of addressing topics theological, pastoral, and international [had] emerged in the Massachusetts Convention. The Spring Convention [was] held alternatively in the UUA (unitarian Universalist Association) and UCC (United Church of Christ) churches with the Convention preacher being from the side other than the host.
"In 1984 the Convention began to sponsor a two day Karl Barth Seminar of Pastors in mid or late June. In the morning a visiting teacher would lead discussion of forty or so pages in the Church Dogmatics. In the afternoon an ecumenical document would be received and discussed.
"Given the many solid sermons preached at the Convention, in 2005 the Convention Archivist began to hold a sermon seminar sometime following the spring Convention to study a past sermon in order to learn the shape of the ministry in Massachusetts for more than three centuries.
"The Convention [was] responsive for distributing the income from the Judah Monis Fund and a modest Convention fund for widows and orphans of Congregational Ministers.
"Programs and publicity [were] the responsibility of officers elected at the spring Convention; a Moderator, Scribe, Treasurer, two Directors from the UUA and two from the UCC with four additional advisers."
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative and financial records of the Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers. Included within the collection are meeting minutes, records of votes, correspondence, memoranda, financial statements, invitations, clippings, speeches, photographs, and publications.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into two series. Within each series, records have been largely arranged in chronological order, by start date, and additionally by topic.
Technical Requirements
In order to access microfilm records, a microfilm reader is required.
In order to access Microsoft Word documents stored on compact disk, a computer with a disk drive and Microsoft Word 2003, or later version, is required.
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Associations, institutions, etc.; Charities -- Massachusetts.; Charity -- Religious aspects.; Clergy conferences.; Conference proceedings.; Ministers -- United States -- Massachusetts.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Congregational Charitable Society; Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers; Minister's Club (Boston, Mass.)
- Administrative records, 1749 2008; 1749-2008
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the administrative records of the Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers. Included in the materials are meeting minutes, committee reports, official correspondence, addresses to the convention, and historical notes.
  - Convention records, 1749 1789; 1749-1789 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Digital Copies
    These convention records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This volume contains the earliest proceedings of the Convention. Included within the volume are meeting minutes, records of votes, and records of collection.
  - Microfilm records, 1749 1789; 1749-1789; circa 1980 (Reel Positive, Reel Negative)
    Restrictions on Access
    Only the positive microfilm reel is available for patron use; the negative reel is restricted for preservation purposes.
    This microfilm reel contains photographic representations of the earliest record book of convention records dating from 1749-1789.
  - Transcriptions, 1749 1928; 1749-1928; 2005-2007 (Box 2)
    Due to preservation concerns, the compact disk and the Microsoft Word documents are not available to library patrons. PDF copies of the transcriptions, however, are available upon request.
    These transcriptions, created by Hal Worthley, are electronic Microsoft Word documents stored on a compact disk. The transcriptions are for the five volumes of convention records dating from 1749-1928.
  - Convention records, 1789 1815; 1789-1815 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    This volume contains the proceedings of the Convention. Included within the volume are meeting minutes, records of votes, lists of members present, and records of collection.
  - Convention records, 1816 1838; 1816-1838 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    This volume contains the proceedings of the Convention. Included within the volume are meeting minutes, records of votes, rules for the Convention and records of collection.
  - Convention records, 1839 1879; 1839-1879 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Convention records, 1880 1928; 1880-1928 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Convention records, 1948 1953; 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Convention records, 1954 1958; 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Convention records, 1959 1963; 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Convention records, 1964 1968; 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Convention records, 1969 1973; 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Convention records, 1974 1976; 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convention records, 1977 1980; 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Convention records, 1981 1982; 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Convention records, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Convention records, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Convention records, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Convention records, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Convention records, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Convention records, 1988 1989; 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Convention records, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Convention records, 1991 1992; 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Convention records, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Convention records, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Convention records, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Convention records, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Convention records, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Convention records, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Convention records, 1999 2000; 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Convention records, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Convention records, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Convention records, 2003 2005; 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Reporting Committee survey, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Addresses, 1891, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Barth seminar topic lists, 1985 2001; 1985-2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - History of the Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Committee report on fasting, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Financial records, 1800 1921; 1800-1921
  This series contains the financial records of the Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers, and related financial records. Included in the materials are ledgers, records of gifts, and fund records.
  - Congregational Charitable Society finances, 1800 1827; 1800-1827 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committee of Inquiry into the Congregation Charitable Society, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ledger of payments, 1839 1903; 1839-1903 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Ledger of payments, 1860 1921; 1860-1881, 1921 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Ledger of payments, 1872 1906; 1872-1906 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Gifts and bequests, 1874 1883; 1874-1883, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fund raising brochures, 1890 1893; 1890-1893 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Society for the Promotion of Theological Education finances, 1893 1902; 1893-1902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unitarian fund, 1901 1916; 1901 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Judah Monis fund, 1902 1904; 1902-1904 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Massachusetts Convention of Congregational Ministers financial records, 1905 1918; 1905-1918 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Evangelical Missionary Society ledger, 1909 1913; 1909-1913 (Box 2, Volume 4)